roncardenasacosta@gmail.com ronaldahmed.github.io

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

- Natural Language Processing: syntactic and semantic parsing, cross-lingual models, statistical machine translation, topic modeling, summarization.
- Machine learning: probabilistic graphical models, structured prediction, deep learning, learning representations, tensor modeling.
- Robotics: symbol grounding problem, robot navigation.
- Language grounding, image and video captioning.

#### CAREER GOAL

To become a fully-fledged XXI century scientist: a scientist with a truly multidisciplinary training, one capable of running a laboratory with students of different disciplines and appropriately integrate their skills to produce cutting-edge research for the benefit of society.

### EDUCATION AND RESEARCH SUMMER SCHOOLS

B.S. Mechatronics Engineering (Robotics) Universidad Nacional de Ingenieria, Lima, Peru. August 2009 - December 2015

- Summa Cum Laude
- Research Advisor: Alberto Coronado

Machine Learning Summer School Kyoto - 2015 Kyoto University. Kyoto, Japan.

August 2015

Summer by Design: Peru

June 2015

ESAN University & Pennsylvania State University. Lima, Peru.

LxMLS: Lisbon Machine Learning Summer School 2014: Learning with Big Data Instituto Superior Tecnologico. Lisbon, Portugal.

July 2014

Competitive Programming Summer School: Maratona do Programação Universidade Estadual de Campinas. Sao Paulo, Brasil.

January 2013

2013

### PUBLICATIONS AND POSTER SESSIONS

R.A. Cardenas, K.S. Bello and A.M. Coronado. "Labor market demand analysis for engineering majors in Peru using Shallow Parsing and Topic Modeling", Machine Learning Summer School Poster Session, Kyoto, Japan, 2015.

R.A. Cardenas, K.S. Bello, A.R. Valle, E.R. Villota and A.M. Coronado. "Panorama of the market demand for Mechanical Engineers in South American Countries". Proceedings of the 2015 ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition (IMECE2015): Volume 5, Engineering Education and Professional Development.

A.R. Valle, K.S. Bello, R.A. Cardenas, E.R. Villota and A.M. Coronado. "Analysis of the Peruvian labor market demand in the area of mining maintenance". Proceedings of the 2nd International Seminar on mining plant and equipment maintenance (MAPLEMIN 2015), Lima, Peru, July, 2015.

## ACHIEVEMENTS, HONORS AND AWARDS

- Research Institute of the Mechanical Eng. Department (INIFIM): Research Grant \$3500 2015
- Universidad Nacional de Ingenieria: Grant for attendance to summer school \$3000 2014,2015
- CONCYTEC Peruvian Science and Technology Research Grant \$1500
- Dean's List 2012-2014
- 7th and 5th place in ACM-ICPC South American Regional Contest by IBM 2012,2014

2012

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### Pennsylvania State University, State College, PA, United States

Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Advisor: Professor Julio Urbina December 2015 - to date

Meteor plasma trial classification using image processing

I am currently working on meteor radar data classification based on its plasma trial reflections. The data consists of radar echoes with low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) values, manually labeled with one of four types of echoes. After frequency filtering, the signal is processed as an image. Morphological, signal duration and range level features are extracted and fed to a linear classifier, achieving 89% Accuracy in average. Work is currently performed remotely from Peru.

## Universidad Nacional de Ingenieria, Lima, Peru

Research Institute of the Mechanical Eng. Department January 2014 - September 2015

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advisor: Professor Alberto Coronado Matutti

Engineering job ads analysis using Topic Models and Shallow Parsing

My job consisted in analyzing the relationship between professional majors in the industry regarding only requirements requested in job ads published in Peruvian job-hunting websites.

I experimented with Latent Dirichlet Allocation, analyzing the effect of inference algorithms (Variational Expectation Maximization and Gibbs Sampling) and the amount of information per document fed to the topic model. This experiment setup consisted in comparing models with the whole document's text and those only with text chunks (requirements and functions requested in the ad) extracted by applying Shallow Parsing beforehand.

The results showed that text chunks allow convergence to a more meaningful minimum in the number of topics in the models over log-likelihood of held-out data, as well as showing clusters of professional majors highly related by the requirements requested by industry.

The project was developed in Python and R.

Spanish Shallow Parsing and Name Entity Recognition from Job Ads

My job consisted in extracting the requirements, functions and professional majors requested in job advertisement in Spanish. I developed a shallow parser to extract requirement and functions as Noun Phrases and Verb Phrases, respectively. Professional majors were extracted by a Name Entity Recognizer. The models implemented were Structured Perceptrons trained over manually annotated data, achieving 91% F1 score in average.

The project also required me to implement automated web data extractors (spiders) and the design and maintenance of relational databases for its storage.

## GISCIA: Artificial Intelligence Research Lab

July 2013 - December 2013

Mechanical Dept., Universidad Nacional de Ingenieria, Lima, Peru

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advisors: Prof. Ricardo Rodriguez and Prof. Ivan Calle

I worked on Simultaneous Localization and Mapping (SLAM) for unmanned ground vehicles. The project included simulation in MatLab and the physical implementation in real time with a differential mobile robot, using a laser range-finder sensor. Two algorithms were compared. First, Grid Localization and Occupancy Grid Mapping. Second, the Extended Kalman Filter with landmark-based mapping.

In addition, I implemented the A\* algorithm for path planning over the estimated grid map.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Empleatron - Start-up Company, Lima, Peru

www.empleatron.com

I worked on front-end and back-end web development of Empleatron: a recommendation system that fetches job ads from Peruvian job-hunting websites to recommend users what skills and knowledge acquire in order to advance in their career path, according to the latest trends in market demand.

### PROGRAMMING & SOFTWARE

• Programming Languages:

Python, C/C++, Java, R, Matlab, JavaScript, Shell scripting.

- Databases: MySQL, SQLite, MongoDB.
- Data Mining Tools: Weka, RStudio, Matlab, LionSolver, Gephi.
- Operating Systems: Linux (Ubuntu, ArchLinux), Windows and Mac OSX.

### TEACHING AND RESEARCH MENTORING

Artificial Intelligence & Control Systems Research Laboratory (GISCIA), Lima, Peru 2013-2015

- Vice-president of GISCIA, organizing seminars, workshops and talks introducing undergraduates to research projects in Machine Learning.
- Training coach of undergraduate students teams for competitive programming contests, such as the ACM ICPC.

# RELEVANT COURSES

- Artificial Intelligence, Autonomous Robotics, Artificial Intelligence for Robotics\*.
- Digital Control Systems, Modern Control, Analysis and Control of Robots.
- Machine Learning\*, Natural Language Processing\*, Intro to Parallel Programming\*.
- Object Oriented Programming, Real-Time Systems Design, Data Communication and Industrial Networks, Digital Signal Processing.
- $\bullet\,$  Statistics and Probabilities, Numerical Methods, Linear Algebra.
- Research Methodology, Project Management.
  - \*: web-based courses

### **LANGUAGES**

English: TOEFL iBT score: 101

Spanish: Native

Portuguese: Elementary proficiency Japanese: Elementary proficiency

## PERSONAL REFERENCES

Julio Urbina

Associate Professor

Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

Pennsylvania State University email: julio.urbina@gmail.com

Alberto Coronado Associate Professor Department of Mechanical Engineering Universidad Nacional de Ingeniería email: am.coronado@gmail.com

Ricardo Rodriguez Associate Professor Department of Mechanical Engineering Universidad Nacional de Ingeniería email: robust@uni.edu.pe